

Mikhail Chugaev

Lead front-end developer in Gdansk, Poland

E-mail: michael.chugaev@gmail.com

Telegram: @mchweb

Github: http://github.com/mchweb

Work permit: PL Permanent resident (Stały pobyt, dostęp do rynku pracy)

8+ years of experience in web development, UI/UX/graphic design and project management. Fundamental knowledge of JavaScript, React.JS, HTML, CSS. Expertise in Agile team management and software development process. Excellent knowledge of Design Systems, skills of Sketch and Adobe Photoshop. Good understanding of Oracle SQL relational databases. General skills of Java/C#/C++. Ability to work both independently and in a multicultural/remote team. Bachelor's Degree in Computer Science.

Work Experience

Lead front-end developer in SRI Infotech, Gdansk, Poland IT company targeted on enterprise software development for financial organizations.

09/2018 — now · Over-the-counter Derivatives team

- Developed and maintained React.JS applications to display, organize and control financial information (real-time ledger) and notify users about various financial events.
- Designed architecture and developed framework-agnostic Typescript boilerplate based on Final Form library to implement high-performance complex interactive forms (hundreds of fields, async calculations and back-end requests, two levels of validations and mapping to custom XML data language). Adopted client's internal React.JS framework to use it as a UI base of these forms.
- Led an agile UI team to migrate applications from outdated technology (Adobe Flex, Flash-based framework) to a modern React.JS stack. Performed code reviews and compiled educational materials for junior developers.
- Maintained a React.JS UI library based on the client's internal framework. Provided feedback and bug reports to the framework development team.
- Worked with product owner to process user feedback, improve UX, design and plan features.
- Worked with the design team to conduct a UX research on the most critical part of the system used to provide and manage trade information. Applied research results to a new version of UI made in compliance with the client's internal Design System.
- Developed several POC's using different technologies (TypeScript, Meteor, Angular), third-party UI libraries (Microsoft Fluent UI, Blueprint.JS, Material UI) and high-performance table frameworks (Handsontable, Tabulator, Autodesk BaseTable, DevExtreme Grid).
- Researched the code of PL/SQL stored procedures to collect and document data formats.

06/2016 — 09/2018 • Enterprise Security Framework team

- Developed (React.JS) and maintained (Java microservices, Oracle DB) high-load application to handle bulk user requests with Excel-like web UI, complex business rules and cross-system data validation. Benchmarked and optimized application performance.
- Established agile approach for the team, designed development pipeline, set up an issue tracker and trained developers.

- Founded a project to migrate several legacy applications to React.JS stack: researched UX
 of existing apps, designed core architecture, selected a set of third-party libraries and
 frameworks, implemented common UI components.
- Ran multicultural front-end and back-end teams. Managed development of key system application used to view and manage security requests.

Full stack web developer, CTO and co-founder of Provocation Studio, Tomsk, Russia Regional start-up digital studio specialized in internet marketing and website development.

05/2015 — **09/2018** ⋅ Web development department

- Developed websites for companies across different areas (internet commerce, restaurants, delivery services, business events, b2b marketing, franchising, educational institutes), including UI design, HTML/CSS markup, JavaScript front-end and back-end, SEO. Worked with the marketing team to optimize conversion rates and increase online sales.
- Analyzed clients' business requirements, prepared project budgets, plans and documentation using the internal PM framework based on IPMA methodology. Managed multiple remote and onsite project teams.
- Worked with the sales team to prepare quotes for new clients and advertise the company.
- Established and managed web development department. Created development workflow, design and coding standards. Worked with HR to find and select candidates, conducted interviews. Trained and mentored staff and interns, created personal development plans. Worked on long-term strategy.

Full stack web developer, graphic and UI designer, C++/C# .NET developer

05/2015 — now · Maintenance of previously developed products

 Continuously communicated directly with clients to provide stable performance and improve previously developed products to help their businesses achieve new goals.

09/2011 - 05/2015 · Freelance

- Designed and developed websites, Android and .NET apps (Windows/Windows Phone) in different areas (accounting, time management, log registers, game dev, productivity tools).
- Graphic design (Adobe Photoshop, InDesign): logo and branding, print materials and media.
- Supported several regional non-profit organizations: launched and maintained Wordpress websites, created content for various media channels (social networks, YouTube, offline), promoted and organized events, led volunteer teams, founded and managed projects.

Education

09/2011 — **05/2015** • Bachelor of **Computer Science and Software Engineering** in National Research Tomsk Polytechnic University, Institute of Cybernetics.

Thesis topic: Monitoring health indicators and preventing health risks using modern wearable devices. Presented and published related articles on XII scientific conference "Microsoft Technologies in the theory and practice of programming".

08/2009 • Summer Programming School for Students, training for ACM competitions.

Skills

Front-end

JavaScript (ES6), TypeScript, React.JS (hooks, contexts, functional components), Redux, Node.JS, npm/yarn, Webpack, HTML5, CSS3 (SCSS/SASS), BEM/SMACSS, Jest, Enzyme. UI components libraries: Bootstrap 3/4, font-awesome, react-widgets, Blueprint.JS, Material Design, Microsoft Fluent UI, CDT4. Other tools/utilities: lodash, moment, final-form, redux-form, react-router, react-intl, grunt/gulp, babel, eslint, prettier, PropTypes, JSDoc, jQuery.

Project and team management

Agile methodologies, Scrum/Kanban, Waterfall. Setting up project pipelines and issue trackers (Trello, YouTrack, Trac, Jira, IBM RTC). Code review, mentoring. Managing remote and multicultural teams. Writing project documentation and user guides, preparing software requirement specification and designing architecture using UML/ER diagrams. Project planning, WBS, Gantt, Burndown charts. Programming interactive Excel spreadsheets.

Design

Graphic and UI (web, desktop, mobile) design, UX research, Design Systems development. Modular systems and grids, typography, responsive web design. Sketching and prototyping. Storybook, Sketch, Figma, Adobe Photoshop, InDesign, Illustrator, Flash, Premiere Pro. Video editing and production.

Back-end

General skills of Java/C#/C++, MySQL/SQL CE/SQLite/Oracle databases, Express.JS, MongoDB, GraphQL, Google Firebase, PHP, MODX CMF, Wordpress, Webasyst Shop-Script, Drupal, XML-technologies (eXistdb).

Software development

Git, SVN. Coding standards, linting. Functional and unit testing. Good understanding of Continuous Integration. IDE/editors: Visual Studio Code, Sublime Text, JetBrains WebStorm, Android Studio, XCode.

Other technical skills

Cross-platform app development (Flutter, Dart). Native Android development, .NET Windows applications. Google App Scripts. Mathcad, TeX. Integrating third-party API's (e.g. payment gateway, analytics). Setting up and maintaining Windows/Linux/OS X workstations, bash, PowerShell. Web hosting setup and maintenance. Advanced skills of Microsoft Office and Google Docs.

Languages

- English: C1 (TPU Certificate in English);
- Polish: B1-B2 (Państwowy egzamin certyfikatowy z języka polskiego jako obcego);
- Russian: native.